The second case I want us to think about
in terms of reward substitution is the
case of a medication called Coumadin.
So, Coumadin is an anti-stroke medication.
It's a relatively good anti-stroke
medication.
It reduces the chances of a second stroke
for about 24% to about 4%.
Now, think about it.
If you had a stroke and this was how much
this medication could reduce your second
stroke, wouldn't you take it?
And Coumadin, by the way, has a few side
effects, particularly ones that have to do
with eating and how you can eat leafy
vegetables and some with bleeding, but
generally has low side effects.
But, sadly, compliance is very low.
It's the same problem.
What's good for you now, and what's good
for you in the future.
Okay, so we have this problem, people had
a stroke don't want to take Coumadin or at
least behave as if they don't want to take
Coumadin.
And we can take this as an indication that
they don't care about taking another,
getting another stroke or we could take it
as an indication that something is wrong
about the incentive structure on how they
get discounted over time.
So, to get into reward substitution we
want two things.
We want to be able to measure something,
and we want to start rewarding or
punishing it.
So, for the measurement perspective
there's a new technology out there.
Maybe not so new, called Internet-enabled
pillbox.
These are pillboxes that every time you
open them it registers on the internet
somewhere and somebody can know that
you've opened the pillbox.
Now, right now, they don't yet measure if
you've taken the pill or not.
But we're going to assume that it's going
to measure both, that you opened the
pillbox and took the pill.
So, now we have this measurement approach.
The question is, how can we reward it?
And how can we punish it?
So, think to yourself for a minute, you
have this pillbox, people are on Coumadin,
what can you do?
So, there's lots of things that we can do.
The easiest thing that probably comes to
mind is paying people.
We can pay people.
Maybe we can charege them.
Maybe we can tell their kids about it or
their parents about it.
Maybe we can tell the doctor about it in
hope that their parents or their doctors
would get them to feel guilty about it.
Maybe we could create a competition
between people who are doing it.
Maybe you can do something more extreme.
Maybe we can create a situation that
unless you take your pill, you can't open
the refrigerator.
Or maybe we can take the pills and cover
them with chocolate, creating immediate
incentives.
But anyway, you could see there's a whole
range of things you could do, the moment
that we need to add incentives to make
that happen.
So, now I want to tell you about the few
experiments we've done on this, and of
course, the potential range of experiments
is just huge and we haven't done many of
them.
So, these are experiments that we have
tried out on George Lowenstein and Kevin
Volpp, and some of their colleagues have
tried it as well.
I'm going to kind of give you a
combination of all of those experiments.
So, what do you think would happen if we
gave people $3 a day to take their
medication on time?
Turns out, nothing much.
What do you think would happen if we gave
people $1,000 a day to take their
medication on time?
I think much like you, the prediction is
that yes, people would take their
medication on time for $1,000 a day.
The problem is we don't have $1,000 a day,
we only have a little bit of money.
So, the next task is to think about how we
can take a small amount of money and make
it look larger, what is called super-size
the incentive.
How we can take the same amount and make
it look larger.
So, one of the things we try is to use a
principle called loss aversion.
And loss aversion is the basic idea that
people like gaining, but we hate losing.
Gaining 3 dollars is exciting, but losing
3 dollars is really miserable and the
misery is much, much larger than the
happiness.
And because of that, if we get people to
lose, it will be more effective.
So, for example, what do you think would
happen if we pre-paid people as if they
took their medication for 3 months, and
then, we would take money away from them
for every day they don't take their
medication, turns out that's more
effective.
You could come up with another idea.
You could say, what if instead of giving
people $3 dollars a day, we would give a
$100 dollars if the took their medication
for awhile.
Then, the amount is larger, but remember
also the discount is higher and future
events need to be much, much larger to
influence us today.
So, you want to bring something to today,
the immediate reward.
By the way, here is something I haven't
tested, but I would love to try it out.
You go to people who are taking Coumadin,
and every morning you wake them up by
showing them a particular kid in Africa
who might get fed today if they take the
medication on time.
It's against $3 and not only that, that
money might go to that kid, they also know
that kid would get to see them in the
evening and say good night to them,
whether they've taken the medication or
not.
And I've predicted under those conditions,
it would be incredibly hard for people not
to give the money, because it would go to
somebody else, to fulfill a really
important goal and you'll have to look
into this person's eyes later in the
evening and feel incredibly guilty, if
they haven't taken their medication.
There's lots of ethical problems, as you
can see, with all of these, but we'll
continue.
Now, here's some stuff that Kevin and
George have done which I think it
incredibly inspiring.
The first thing they did was they said,
you know what?
Money is great, but people love lotteries.
In fact, the columnists often call
lotteries a taxation on stupidity because
they expected value is usually quite very,
very low.
But nevertheless people love lotteries.
That's why we have Vegas.
That's why we have random reinforcements.
So, what do you think would happen if
instead of giving people $3 in cash for
sure, you give them 10% chance of making
$30?
Turns out, that's much more exciting.
In fact, the ideal way to create a lottery
is to create a lottery with two things.
You have one big reward that you could
dream about, but get very, very
infrequently.
But that fulfills the aspiration level.
And then, you have smaller rewards that
have a higher probability of actually
being given out.
So, from time to time, if you're in the
system you can get some reward and it
reminds you that you have a chance of
getting the big one.
If you only had the big one, then most
days you don't get anything.
It's not that exciting.
So, you want a combination of a really big
reward and some small rewards that keep
people in the game and feel excited.
So, lotteries are good, but they didn't
stop there.
They added another component called
regret.
And regret is a really interesting idea
and it's worthwhile stopping and thinking
about it for a while.
So, what is regret?
Regret is about the fact that our
happiness with where we are in life is not
about where we are, it's a comparison
between where we are and where we think we
could have been.
And if this other place where we think we
could have been is better than where we
are, we feel terrible.
And if this other place where we think we
could have been is worse than where we
are, we feel good about it.
So, here's an example.
When do you think you would be more
unhappy?
If you missed your flight by 2 minutes or
by 2 hours?
Of course, by two minutes.
But why?
You're stuck at O'Hare with the same bad
airport food, with the same unpleasant
airport.
Why you're more unhappy if you missed your
flight by 2 minutes?
Because you can imagine the many ways you
would have made it.
You could say to yourself, if the TSA
agent had one more IQ point, everything
would have gone well, this is the security
people.
You could say to yourself, if the person
in front of me understood what taking your
shoes off mean, everything would have been
fine.
There are many, many ways in which you can
imagine how you would have been in this
other reality, and then, the contrast
between these two realities is incredibly
salient.
If you missed your by 2 hours, there's no
way for you to imagine that reality.
So, it's not creating the same contrast.
By the way, it's a personal observation.
I should tell you that I think that one of
the reasons that I think I'm generally
happy in life is that because after
sustaining a very serious injury, I have
lots of reminders about that injury and
the contrast between where I am now and
where I was for many years in hospital, is
incredibly clear to me.
I think that if I had an injury that I had
the same misery for a long time, but then,
it went away, I don't think I would have
had the same benefit.
So, while these scars and some of the pain
that they give me everyday is have some
unpleasantness, I think it is useful as a
reminder of how things could have been.
It makes it harder for me to forget this
contrast between where I am now and where
I was, and therefore, I think I am happier
because of that.
This is not a good experiment, of course
just my intuition.
In a very different domain, in some of the
Olympics, they took pictures of people who
won medals.
And they asked the question of what
determines the size of the smile.
And you would think that the gold, people
with gold would smile the most, silver
less, and bronze less.
But when you actually look at it, it's
gold, bronze, silver.
The people with silver are the one who are
smiling the least.
How could that be?
Well, put yourself in the mindset of
somebody who just won the silver medal.
What are they thinking?
What's going through their mind?
They probably say to themselves, I was
this close.
In fact, it's probably not something that
is this close like in the Olympics, like
it could be milliseconds.
And what is the person with bronze
thinking?
They say, well at least I'm here on this
stage.
Look at all the other people that didn't
get here at all.
So, now you can see how in this case, but
also probably in areas of your own life,
happiness is not determined by where we
are, but what reality we are comparing
ourselves to.
And if this reality is better, we feel
miserable.
If this reality is worse, we feel good
about it.
So, let's take regret and roll it back for
experiment with Coumadin.
Imagine that we have a big gorup of people
taking Coumadin.
And imagine part of these people are
taking the medication on time and another
part of these people are not taking the
medication on time.
If we just do the, the rewards by
lotteries to the people who've taken the
medication on time, we take all the people
who took the medication on time, we sample
10% of them and we give them the lottery
ticket.
We call them up, we say congratulations
and we give them the lottery tickets.
Now, there's no regret.
The people who are winning feel good and
the people who are not taking their
medication, don't really know that
anything bad has happened.
How do we add regret to the equation?
We're doing it by giving a lottery ticket
for everybody in the sample.
We give it to the people who've taken
their medication on time and we giving it
to the people who did not take the
medication on time.
And if it's somebody who did not take
their medication on time that comes up in
the lottery, we call them up, and we say,
congratulations, it is your lucky day.
The stars are smiling on you.
You're the winner of the coveted lottery.
Sadly, you did not take your pill on time,
so you're not getting the prize, you're
not getting the reward.
Now, think about it, this is the essence
of regret.
Now, you can say to yourself, my goodness,
there was a tiny little act in the morning
of taking the medication that if I would
have engaged on that, I would been on the
other side of that fence.
And I really don't want to be on that
other side of the fence again.
And now what happens?
You combine lotteries and you combine
regret and compliance rate goes up to
about 97%-98%.
Now, here's the thing, when you look at
something like Coumadin, you say many
people just don't take their medication
regularly on time, and it's terrible.
It's a blood thinner.
You should take your medication on time if
you're on Coumadin.
Luckily, we can add reward substitution.
We can add $3, potentially could add
shame.
We could add all kinds of other things and
not only that, we can think about how to
maximize that incentive.
We can take, for example, $3 and think
about how we super-size it.
How do we add lotteries to it, randomness?
How do we add counterfactual thinking and
regret and by doing so, get people to
behave as if they care.
About getting another stroke, eventually
getting people to behave in a way that is
better for them, better for the families
and of course better for the health care
system.