Hi my name is Hedy Kober.
And I'm psychologist and a cognitive
therapist scientist at Yale University.
And if you remember one thing from my
talk today, let it be this.
If you want to you can train yourself to
have better self-control.
But before we start going to take a step
back and try to define, what is
self-control?
I like to think about it in a few
different ways.
Self control, or self regulation, I am
going to use these terms interchangeably,
is what you exercise when you want to
change something about how you'd
otherwise think, feel or behave in any
given situation.
And you can think about situations when
you need to use self control as those in
which you have options for your emotions,
your thoughts or your behaviors.
And you need to exert some effort in
choosing one over the other.
You might ask yourself why would I need
to exert some effort?
Well, typically is because one option is
harder to choose.
And that's typically the one that's
better for you in the long term.
Now, you may have heard self-control
defined as a set of problems that
differentiate between what's now and
what's later.
And so the idea is that one of the
options comes naturally in this moment.
like when you're tempted by cake, and you
really want to eat it and it looks really
good.
But the other option is to control
yourself, and you need to exert some
effort not to be tempted by this cake.
Now, self-control can be exercised in
different domains, as I've already
alluded to.
There's control of thought, for example
when you have a persistent thought.
Maybe about something that upset you,
something that didn't go quite as well as
you had hoped.
Maybe someone broke your heart.
the control of emotions.
Sometimes you have negative emotion.
You're angry at someone, you're upset
about something.
And there are ways that you can reduce
that kind of negative emotion.
Of course, there's also control of
craving or temptation.
Which is kind of the canonical way that
we think about self control.
And one of the ways that I'm going to
talk about it today.
And then there's the control of behavior,
which is really linked to, to, to these
other forms of control.
and this includes how to stay focused on
a task.
But it also includes choosing to behave
in a particular way that's better for
you.
Or stopping yourself from behaving in
ways that are slightly less optimal.
And the amazing thing is that we have to
exercise self control all the time in
many, many different kinds of contexts.
For example, you are exercising self
control right now because you're not
taking a nap and you're probably not
eating cake.
You're watching me talk about self
control and that probably requires some
self control on your part.
and to illustrate that, I want you to
find more examples of when you exercise
self control successfully in the last
month.
So you probably though of a few times
When you've exercised self control
successfully and you can give yourself a
point for each one of these instances.
for example, maybe you criticized someone
in your head.
But you didn't tell them about it because
you thought it was going to hurt their
feelings.
Maybe you were really tired, even
exhausted, but you still brush your teeth
before bedtime.
how about you got irritated walking down
the street, someone bumped into you.
Maybe you were in traffic.
But you didn't yell at anybody, you
didn't act on it in any kind of way.
and all of these are examples of
successful self-control, and good for
you.
Of course, the other side of that is also
really important.
We, not infrequently fail at
self-control, and the classic way to
think about this are times when you've
done that recently.
Right?
So maybe you texted while you were
driving or you were tempted to eat
dessert even when you thought you
shouldn't.
And what you can see from both kinds of
these examples is that self control is
part of almost everything that you do.
And that you do this with varying levels
of success.
But there's something that is central and
really important to many, many aspects of
your life.
And indeed, research has shown repeatedly
that being able to exercise self-control
effectively is associated with long-term
health, long-term happiness and long-term
success.
And it doesn't mean that exercising
self-control in a particular moment would
make you happy.
But people who exercise self-control in
general.tend to behave more consistently
with their long term goals and are
typically happier and healthier as a
result.
In the first set of experiments that
really showed that nicely was Walter
Mischel's Marshmallow Test Experiments.
And in these experiments, kids are put in
a room in front of a table where a
marshmallow or a cookie are presented and
they're given a choice.
You can either eat the marshmallow now.
Or you can wait 15 minutes and get two
marshmallows.
And for kids, marshmallows are really
exciting.
They love marshmallows.
If you've ever met kids, you know that's
true.
And so, for them, the temptation to eat
the marshmallow or the cookie right now
is really high.
And the question is, of course, can they
regulate their craving?
Can they control their behavior and delay
their gratification?
And before I tell you what the answer is,
I want you to think back, for when you
were a kid.
Three, or four, or five, just like the
kids in these experiments, do you think
you'd be able to wait for a second
marshmallow or a second cookie?
Well, I wanted to know what the answer
was for me and I thought about it and I
wasn't exactly sure.
And so, I called my mother.
And my mother said this.
She said, you were so stubborn as a
child, that maybe to prove a point you
might have waited, but you also had a
really, really hard time delaying
gratification.
And then, she thought about it another
moment and she said, and if it was
pretzels, there was no way that you would
have waited because they were your
favorite.
And, of course, I'm just one example.
But the idea is that there's variability.
And the results in these experiments were
exactly that.
Kids varied in their ability to wait.
Some kids couldn't wait at all.
As soon as the experimenter left the
room, [SOUND] immediately they ate the
cookie or they ate the marshmallow.
Other kids managed to wait the entire 15
minutes, and at the end of the experiment
they got two cookies or two marshmallows.
But the second and really, really
important finding is that the number of
minutes that kids waited ended up
predicting a whole host of outcomes for
their lives.
They were better l-, better rated by
their teachers in school just a few years
later.
They got better SAT scores in high
school.
They made more money, they, didn't go to
jail and didn't use as many drugs when
they were in their 20s and 30s.
So many many long time successes were
associated with better self control.
And I'll get back to these experiments in
just a few minutes to make another point.
But what we can learn from this now is
that the ability to exercise self control
is incredibly important.
Has great implications for life.
And in fact, a recent set of experiments
has shown that self control is a better
predictor of school performance in kids
than even IQ.
And as a researcher, as soon as I
realized how important self control was,
I knew that we needed to find out more
about how it works.
And I started reading a lot about it and
one of the metaphors that I came to
really like was the metaphor of self
control as a mental muscle.
And I really like it because self control
ends up being like a mental muscle in
three important ways.
The first way is that if in any given
moment, if you exercise the right
technique or the right strategy, you can
lift much heavier weights.
You can do a lot more with this muscle.
The second way is that this muscle
doesn't have, infinite capacity.
It's somewhat limited.
if you use the muscle a lot earlier in
the day, you might have less ability to
use it later in the day, just like with
real muscles.
And the third thing is really cool, I
think.
Potentially, the most amazing, which is,
you can teach yourself or train yourself
to have much stronger mental muscle self
control.
That will allow you to do much more over
time.
Okay, let's break it down.
So the first was technique, right.
And the idea that if you learn the right
technique and exercise it in the moment
you can exhibit much better self control.
There are already strategies you can set
up ahead of time to ensure that you'll
have better self control and one such
strategy is to use reward substitution.
Maybe there's something that you don't
want to do.
You can promise yourself a reward.
instead of the task itself.
Or in my case, for example, every time
that I submit my taxes, I take myself out
to a really nice dinner at my favorite
restaurant.
Another way to do this is to set a
contract ahead of time with yourself,
sometimes called Ulysses contracts.
Where, if you don't do something that you
maybe want to do or need to do you will
incur some kind of penalty.
So a friend of mine, for example, had a
deal with her husband, if she doesn't go
to the gym three times a week, he ends up
donating to the charity that she really,
really, doesn't like.
And so this motivates her to go to the
gym.
But we can't use this for everything,
right?
Imagine you're already at dinner, you
didn't set up a contract.
But you really want to make sure that you
don't get tempted by this luscious,
wonderful cake that just arrived at your
table.
How do you do this?
Is there a way in the moment to control
your craving and delay your
gratification?
Well, it turns out that even from these
Walter-Michele marshmallow experiments,
we know that that's true.
Right?
Some kids could really wait as much as 15
minutes.
And so adults must be able to do that as
well.
Well, the cooler finding, I think, in
these marshmallow experiments, is that
even the kids who couldn't wait, if the
experimenter taught them some strategies
right then and there.
Suddenly, they were able to wait much
longer.
Can we do the same thing with adults?
Well, the first thing that's difficult to
do with adults is to get them to really
want marshmallows.
So we can't get them to want to devour
marshmallows, but we can tempt them with
other kinds of foods.
And this is really how food commercials
work, right?
You see an ad for this creamy, beautiful
ice cream, and you think to
yourself,[SOUND] that looks so good.
I want to eat that right now.
and so that's exactly what I did in some
of the experiments that we ran in my lab.
We show people pictures of food.
We show cigarette smokers pictures of
cigarettes.
We take individuals who smoke crack
cocaine and we show them pictures of
crack cocaine and other people smoking
crack cocaine and what results is a state
of craving.
They're really tempted.
They want to eat.
They want to smoke.
What we do then is we teach them a very
simple strategy for regulation of
craving.
We call this the Regulation of Craving
task or the ROC task.
And what we tell them to do is we tell
them to think about all the reasons that
they have not to eat the chocolate cake,
not to smoke cigarettes, not to smoke
crack, right?
Think about the negative consequences
that they might incur if they engage in
this behavior.
so, for example.
If I, if I were a participant in my own
experiment, and I saw a picture of
chocolate cake.
I might think to myself, well it looks
really good.
But if I eat it it might be bad for my
weight.
It will probably over time, raise my
blood pressure.
be bad for my health.
I might have a higher risk of diabetes.
It's really bad for me.
I really, really don't want to do this.
Not to mention, I might feel bad about
myself if I eat this cake.
And what did we find?
We found that when individuals use this
strategy to regulate their craving.
they actually reported much lower
craving.
And even more than reporting lower
craving, they reported that they wanted
to eat this food less, they wanted to
smoke less, they wanted to engage less in
these behaviors when they thought about
these consequences.
And then, when we looked at their brain
activity, what we found is that using
these techniques allows them to recruit
parts of their brain, the prefrontal
cortex, which we know is associated with
better self control.
And in turn what we saw is a reduction in
brain activity in regions of their brain
that we know gives rise to craving.
So in using these strategies they were
better able to control their craving and
they were able to change the way their
brain worked in that moment.
Now, of course, it, this didn't work
perfectly.
It didn't work for everybody.
But it worked for a lot of our
participants.
And so, this is something that you might
want to try next time you're in that kind
of situation.
Now, the second thing that makes self
control like a mental muscle, is the fact
that the ability of this muscle might be
limited.
For example, when you go to the gym you
maybe can do a certain set of exercises
with the same muscle, but you can't
really go on forever.
And maybe after you finish being at the
gym, you can't really lift as many heavy
boxes as you would if you hadn't gone to
the gym and exercised your muscle.
Well, self control turns out to be
similar.
There's now many, many studies that have
shown, that when you use self-control
later in the day, you might have a little
bit less self-control available.
and there are different ideas about why
this happens, but either way, what I want
to tell you today is that you can really
anticipate that this is going to happen.
Notice when you feel like people call
this depleted and that there are things
that you can do to make this better.
So for example one finding is that if
people pace themselves, knowing that you
have to go to dinner tonight and exercise
self-control in the face of dessert.
you can pace yourself throughout the day
and not use as many of your self control
resources so that you have some spare
left.
the second thing is that people found
that positive emotion reverse this effect
of depletion.
So if you feel like you've already
exercised a lot of self control, maybe
you don't have a lot left right in this
moment.
you can watch a funny movie.
It turns out that, after this funny
movie, a lot of people show kind of a
return of this self control strength.
The third finding that had come out
fairly recently, is the idea that
individuals who believe that exercising
self control won't deplete them, don't
get quite as depleted.
And you can try to do this, in your own
time.
The third and I think most amazing way in
which self-control is like a muscle is
the fact that you can train it.
Now, we know from clinical psychology
that there are treatments that help
individuals exercise better self-control.
For example, in a treatment called
cognitive behavioral therapy for
addictions or substance abuse disorders,
individuals who use drugs learn how to
use the same strategy that I told you
about just a few minutes ago.
to reduce their craving for drugs, and
reduce their drug use.
And indeed that kind of treatment is one
of the best treatments we have for
addiction.
And in a finding from Cathy Carol's lab
at Yale we recently learned that those
individuals who learn how to to use a
strategy the best at the end of
treatment.
Are also those individuals who end up
using the least drugs and doing the best
over time.
we also have shown that individuals who
undergo this treatment actually show
changes in the prefrontal cortex from
before to after treatment.
With a prefront, their prefrontal cortex
actually becomes more efficient after
treatment.
So more able to carry out these self
control operations.
But of course, these treatments are
complex they're long, they often happen
over the course of several months.
What about briefer training self-control,
can that help if you don't go through an
entire treatment that have other kinds of
components to it?
Well luckily, we have evidence now, that
there's shorter kinds of training you can
do to improve your self-control.
For example, in a series of studies that
we recently completed in my lab, we've
shown that with half an hour of training.
using the kind of strategy that I told
you about we can train cigarette smokers
to regulate their craving.
And over the course of the next two
weeks, with just half an hour of
training, they report smoking a lot less.
So we are able to help individuals
control their smoking by training them in
using this particular strategy.
Now, of course, this is a very direct
kind of practice, right, you practice
using a strategy To regulate your
craving, and you get better at regulating
your craving and you smoke less.
But it turns out that there's also
indirect training that you can do.
And training in smalls acts of self
control can also strengthen your self
control muscle and help you have better
self control in general.
So what are some examples?
some researchers have asked people to
turn open doors or open cabinets for an
entire week with their non-dominant hand.
So if you're right-handed, you would do
this with your left hand, if you're
left-handed, you would do this with your
right hand.
And it turns out that at the end of this
week, people were better at exercising
self-control in general.
Other kinds of exercises include going to
the gym regularly, refraining from eating
sweets and even using a hand grip.
All of these kind of training improve
self-control in general.
Of course, nothing that I told you today
will help you if you're missing one key
ingredient, and that is the motivation to
change.
Well it turns out, that if you don't have
the motivation to change, how are you
going to learn the right techniques?
and if you do have the motivation to
change not only can you learn the right
techniques, but you can apply them in the
moment.
You can prepare yourself for being
depleted and counteract it if you need
to.
And of course, practice, practice,
practice to increase your self-control.
this is the one thing that you are
supposed to remember from this lecture.
If you want to, you can work to have
better self-control.
And to illustrate this importance of
motivation, I'm going to tell you the one
joke that I know to tell.
How many psychologists does it take to
change a light bulb?
One, but only if the light bulb really
wants to change.
Thank you and good luck.