So what we thought, was that maybe what's
going on here, and there's a fudge factor,
that people try to balance two forces.
On one hand, we want to look at the mirror
and feel that we're good honest wonderful
moral people, that's the psychological
benefit of viewing ourself positively.
On the other hand, we want to benefit from
cheating, that's the economic incentive.
Now usually you would say, you can have
one or the other.
How can you both think of yourself as a
wonderful honest person, and benefit from
cheating at the same time?
It doesn't work.
Well, maybe, maybe due to our flexible
cognitive ability, maybe due to the fact
that we can rationalize things very
quickly, as long as we cheat just a little
bit, we can both benefit from cheating,
just a little bit, and we can still view
ourself as honorable people.
And that's what we call the fudge factor.
That the moment we start creating a
dishonest behavior, there's a range before
it invokes a different concept of
ourselves.
And in that range, we could both be
dishonest, and still think of our self as
honest people.
So how do we test this kind of a theory?
The first thing we wanted to do, is we
wanted to take some approaches and shrink
the fudge factor.
We want to get people to cheat less by,
but not by manipulating their economic
variables.
And the first idea for this came from a
little joke.
And the joke is that a guy goes to the
Rabbi and he said, Rabbi you wouldn't
believe what happened to me, somebody
stole my bicycle from Synagogue.
And the Rabbi is appalled, he say I can't
believe this is happening, this is awful,
this is terrible.
I tell you what you do, come to synagogue
next week and sit in the front row.
And as we go over the Ten Commandments,
turn around, and look at everybody in the
aisles.
And when we get to Thou Shalt Not Steal,
see who can't look you in the eyes, you'll
know that's your thief.
The guy's very excited about the advice.
The rabbi is very excited about the
advice.
He comes to synagogue, sit in the front
row, turns around during the Ten
Commandments.
He comes to the Rabbi at the end of the
service.
He says, "Rabbi, you wouldn't believe it.
What a fantastic idea, it worked just like
a charm.
The moment, the moment we got to "Thou
shall not commit adultery" I remembered
where I left my bike.
Now where, [laugh] where is this joke
leading us?
You probably think to yourself where is
the experiment in this thing?
Well, we went to UCLA, and we asked about
500 students to try and recall the ten
commandments.
Interestingly by the way, none of them
could recall all ten commandments and
quite a few of them invented new ones, but
that's a topic for a different discussion.
But after getting them to try and recall
the ten commandments we gave them the same
math task.
And we were wondering how much would they
cheat after just thinking about the ten
commandments.
What did we see?
Zero cheating.
Now it wasn't as if the people remembered
moral commandments.
Presuming the more religious people
cheated less, and the people who could
hardly remember any commandment cheated
more?
No, nobody cheated.
In fact even when we take self-declared
atheist, and we asked them to swear on the
Bible, and then we give them a chance to
steal from us in the same way in the same
task, we see no cheating whatsoever.
So this suggests that it's not about
cost-benefit, it's not about people
thinking about heaven or hell and this is
why they should be honest or not.
It's about reminding people about their
own morality, because even if you remind
people about morality that is not their
own, like atheists are being reminded
about the Ten Commandments.
Being, thinking, just thinking about
morality, shrinks our fudge factor, get us
to be a bit more careful about our own
behavior and therefore allowing us to be
more, more honest.
Now, eh, this was kind of an interesting
idea.
But you know religion and civic society
and there's all kinds of issues whether we
want to involve religion in many, in many
places, so the next thing we decided to do
was to try a secular version of it.
And at the university it's very natural to
use the honor code.
So we did this model at MIT and at Yale.
We went to the students.
And we edit one sentence to the beginning
of the test.
I understand that this short survey falls
under the MIT or Yale honor code
signature.
What happened?
People signed, they did the test, they
shredded, no cheating whatsoever.
And no cheating whatsoever despite the
fact that neither MIT nor Yale actually
have an honor code.
Now this means that those two universities
don't have specific costs associated with
cheating.
But nevertheless, being reminded about
some moral element decreased cheating so
dramatically we couldn't detect any.
Now in contrast, we went to another
university that has a very strong honor
code.
We went to Princeton.
Princeton has a very strong honor code.
They take the freshmen and they give them
a, a week long, a lesson on honesty.
There's lectures and discussion, the a
capella group has a song about it, it's,
the whole week is a crash course on
morality.
We waited two weeks, after these freshmen
finished with their crash course on
morality, and we tempted them to cheat in
the same way, some of them with signing,
some of them without signing.
What do you think happened?
Would the Princeton student be different
than the Yale, and MIT student?
They were not.
When they did not sign the code, they
cheated just like the MIT and Yale
student.
When they signed, they didn't cheat just
like the MIT and Yale students.
So this is kind of a good news, bad news.
The bad news, is that a week-long crash
course on morality doesn't seem to have
any measurable effects two weeks down the
road, at least not the Princeton version
of it.
And I think the same thing applies to many
corporate lessons and, university, classes
and so on, in morality.
Morality training just doesn't seem to be
that effective, that's the bad news.
The good news, is that reminding people
about their own morality, whether it has
consequences or not when, like Princeton,
it has really huge penalty if you're being
caught cheating versus MIT and Yale, that
you don't, that seemed to actually make a
big difference.
So rather than thinking about global
cultural changes, that might be very nice
but very hard to achieve.
Maybe what we need to focus on, is to
think about how we change things just
before people are tempted to be dishonest.
In the next version of this we tried one
more thing, we tried some people signed
first, before they did the test, and some
people signed afterward.
What did we find?
If you signed first, people don't cheat.
If you sign at the end, people cheat just
a lot, because it's finished, you finished
cheating.
And so with this idea we went to the IRS
and we said to the IRS think about all the
IRS forms.
Right.
People finish the IRS form and then at the
end, many pages later you sign.
At that point your signature is not doing
anything to prime morality.
And nobody's going to say, oh, yes, let me
sign, let me go back and fix things.
No, cheating is over by that time.
The form is being finished.
So we said to the IRS, why don't you put
the signature up front?
Why don't you start by signing?
Eh, well the people at the IRS said this
is illegal, because signature is meant for
verification, not for priming morality.
And you can actually see how signature has
these two very different functions, if
it's in the front or in the back.
So we said okay, we understand this.
Why don't you put both the signature in
the front and the signature in the back?
Well, they said, the people at the IRS
said, well, that's confusing.
I don't know if you've seen the IRS forms
recently, or the IRS tax a code, but you
know the idea that signing twice is
confusing, baffled me a little bit.
I was speechless.
But then I said okay, if that's confusing
how about if the first item on the tax
return, would ask people would you give
$25 to a task force to fight corruption.
And we said this is not just a signature,
this is asking people whether they want to
put money towards something.
And if people commit, and commit money
towards something, there's a good chance
that later on, they will continue acting
in a more, eh, appropriate, honest,
behavior.
Plus, we said, the people that don't want
to give money a task force to fight
corruption, maybe you can audit them, to a
higher degree.
Anyway, the IRS did not want to talk to us
anymore.
But we went to talk to an insurance
company.
Interesting, this was insurance company
that insures, eh, homes and houses, lots
of personal things.
And they told us, that they think that
their cheating, that they are seeing, is
very much like in our experiments.
They think that very few people invent
burglaries, and arsenies, and larceny, and
car theft, but lots and lots and lots of
people, when something bad happen
exaggerated by 10, 15%.
And they estimated that these exaggeration
cost industry about $24 billion, a year
which is lots and lots of money.
I know we through lots of big numbers
these days, but 24 billion is still a big
number.
So we came up with all kinds of ideas.
We said, what if when people were waiting
on hold, you would play religious music
for them?
What would happen if you would put images
of eyes, as if they're being watched, on
the form?
What if you got them to sign first?
What if you got some declaration that had
to do something with religion as well?
We had all kind of ideas about how you
increase, em, honesty.
But you know, we had lots of good ideals
and they had lawyers and when you have
good ideas and lawyers together in the
same room nothing ever happen.
So after six months of trying very hard to
get this, nothing was done.
But my contact in this insurance company
felt very bad for me.
So he came to me and he gave me this form,
where you mail it to people and you ask
them to report how many miles you drove
last year.
Now imagine you got one of those form,
what would you want to shade the number,
up or down?
If you shade it up, it would mean your
premium would go up, if you shade it down
your premium will go down, so you'll
probably want to shade it down.
They gave us 20,000 forms and we did one
thing, we moved the signature line to the
top.
Half the people got the signature on the
top first and half the people got it at
the bottom.
Some people signed first, and then filled
the mileage, some people fill the mileage
then sign.
What did we see?
There was a difference of about 2400 miles
on average.
The people who signed first reported
driving 2400 miles more.
Now we don't know if they didn't cheat at
all, but we know the cheating was much
reduced.
And that actually gives me great hope that
we can create those small interventions
and get them to work not just in the lab,
but get them in the field in all kinds of
other versions like that.
Okay, so all that was about how we shrink
the fudge factor.
How do we get people to, at the moment,
tolerate less of their own immortality and
be more careful about what they're doing?
The next question we wanted to ask, was
how do you get people to cheat more, how
do you expand the fudge factor?
And of course, this is not an objective to
increase cheating in society, but for the
purpose of understanding it, what kind of
things would get people to cheat more and
nevertheless feel comfortable with
themselves.
And the idea here also came from a little
joke.
And the little joke is, that little Johnny
comes home from school with a note from
the teacher that says that little Johnny
stole a pencil from the kid who was
sitting next to him.
And Johnny's father is furious and he
said, Johnny I'm humiliated and
embarrassed and I'm angry.
And you're grounded for three weeks and
just wait until your mother comes.
You never, never, never steal a pencil
from the kid who is sitting next to you.
And beside Johnny if you need something,
if you need a pencil you know very well
you can just say something.
You can just ask and I will bring you
dozens of pencils from work.
If you find this funny it's probably
because you realize that taking a pencil
from work feels very differently than
taking 10 cents from petty cash box, even
if you were going to use those 10 cents to
buy yourself a pencil.
Perhaps the moment something becomes
multiple steps removed from money, there
are more stories we can tell ourselves.
Right, you could say the workplace wants
us to have these pencils, otherwise they
wouldn't put them there.
Or you could say other people take them,
as well.
Or you could say, even if I take them and
give them to my kids, they will leave me
alone and that would allow me to answer
two more emails.
Good for the workplace.
And all of those distance allow us to tell
ourselves stories, allow us to rationalize
things that basically create this ability
to cheat more, but nevertheless to feel
better about ourselves.
So the first experiment we did on this, is
I walked around campus and I put six packs
of Cokes, in some common refrigerators.
Now these were refrigerators that
everybody had their own stuff, but
multiple people had their stuff in the
same refrigerator.
And I basically wanted to see what is the
half lifetime of Coke.
How long will it take for my Cokes to
disappear?
And basically within 72 hours no Cokes
were left there, everything was gone.
Now in contrast, I took a plate with six
$1 bills, I put in the same refrigerators
and I waited.
And now what happened, nobody touched a
single dollar.
Now the students could have taken a
dollar, putting it in the nearby vending
machine, get coke and change, but nobody
did.
When something is directly about money, we
feel very differently about it.
When something is removed from money, more
abstract, there are some stories we can
tell ourselves, rationalizing and,
therefore, we can be more dishonest.
Now this is not an ideal experiment,
because it's often the case that you open
the refrigerator and you find Coke.
It's not so common that you open the
refrigerator and find a plate with six $1
bills, so something must have been very
strange.
So we did the same experiment, the same
principle with the same matrix test and
here's the experiment.
Some people got the sheet, solved it, came
to the experimenter, looked him in the
eyes and said, Mister experimenter I
solved x problems, give me x dollars.
So they looked him in the eyes and they
cheated for dollars.
The second group did the same thing, but
when they came to the experiment, the guy
looked him in the eyes, and they said, "Mr
Experimenter, I solved x problems; give me
x tokens.
So they were lying not for money, they
were lying for something that is tokens.
And we gave them tokens.
They took 12 feet to the side; they walked
12 feet to the side, and they replaced
these tokens for money.
Now they were lying for a pencil, but it
was a pencil for only a few seconds.
It was one step removed from money, but
for a very, very short duration.
What happened?
Our participant doubled their cheating in
that condition.
And by the way this is for me one of the
most worrisome experiments we've ever
done.
Because if you think about it, we're
moving to becoming a cashless society, as
consumers there's all these discussions
about digital wallets.
On Wall Street there's of course all these
complex financial tools that are becoming
more steps removed from money.
People own more and more things like stock
options and things that are removed from
money.
And if being close to money and observing
it directly is what's keeping us
relatively honest, is it the case that in
all kinds of domains of life, electronic
wallets, financial markets, the more this
distance is increasing, the more we can
allow ourselves to both be dishonest and
think of our self as hon-, as honest
people.
And that really, really worries me.
So that was the first thing that got
people to cheat more, distance from money.
The next thing we wondered, is we wondered
what happened when you watched other
people cheat in an egregious way?
After all we open the newspaper everyday
and we see all kinds of stories about big
cheaters.
What is the affect of observing other
people in society does to our own
morality?
So we repeated this same experiment with
two changes.
The first one was that we prepaid people,
everybody got an envelope with all the
money as if they solved all the problems.
And we asked them at the end, to pay us
back the money they didn't make and to
take only the money they deserve.
That was the first change.
The second change was that we hired an
acting student.
That acting student sat in the front seat
in the, in the classroom.
And 30 seconds into the experiment, he
raised his hand and said, excuse me, I
solved everything, what do I do now?
Now imagine you were in that experiment.
You're solving, you're working very hard,
you're still on problem number one, and
all of a sudden you see somebody who
claimed that they've solved everything.
You know for sure, without cheating,
there's no other way.
And the experimenter said, "You've solved
everything?
You're free to go." And you see that
person taking the envelope with all the
money and leaving the room.
What would happen now to your own
morality?
Lots and lots of moral people cheat.
Now there's two ways to interpret this
result.
One is to say this is about cost/benefit
analysis.
Before you saw that guy cheating in an
egregious way, you thought to yourself, I
don't know what's the cost of cheating
here.
Maybe they will catch me.
Maybe somebody would run after me.
But after you saw a demonstration of
somebody cheating in this egregious way
and nobody going after them, you say
there's no cost here let me cheat.
The other possibility, is that it's not
about the cost benefit analysis, but its
about what you call social proof.
Its about giving people a demonstration
that people like them, from their society,
from their community, students at the same
university are cheating in such
circumstance.
And maybe because of that it is okay to
cheat in those things, not from a moral
perspective, but from a social agreement
persepctive this is the behavior.
Here is someone who has done it and is not
even feeling sorry about that.
As an analogy you can think about what if
everybody around you is downin-,
downloading illegal content, at some
point, do you start saying, okay, this is
just, I guess what is okay to do.
To separate those two things, we tried
these two explanations, we tried two
things.
The first one, is that instead of the
student cheating, we asked him to just
raise his hand and said excuse me, but
with this set of instructions, can't I
just say I solved everything and take all
the money and go home?
And the instructor said you know what?
You can, it's up to you.
So now it was clear that from a cost
benefit analysis you can cheat and get
away with it, but there was no example of
somebody actually doing it.
What happened now when we did this?
Cheating did not go up it actually went
down.
We did another version of this and in the
other version we changed the outfit of
this acting student.
We ran this experiment at Carnegie Mellon.
All the students were Carnegie Mellon.
The acting student was a Carnegie Mellon
student.
They were all from that group.
In the second experiment, we ran this, eh,
version, but we dressed the acting student
with University of Pittsburgh outfit.
Now, when they stood up and say, excuse
me, I solved everything, and walked home
with all the money, you would still know
that it's the same cost benefit analysis,
that now in this experiment you're not
going to be punished, but there was no
social proof.
It wasn't as if somebody from your social
group, from your friends, from your
community is cheating this way, it's those
other people from this other university
that we don't like so much.
It's those people who are immoral.
What happened now?
Cheating did not go up, it went down.
And basically I think that two things
happened.
The first one, was that people were
reminded about morality and honesty by
seeing an egregious act of misbehavior, a
little bit like the ten commandments
version.
But it wasn't their group, it was what we
called an out group, it was somebody else
behaving this way.
And therefore they did not take it as a
signal that it's okay for them to do this
as well.
So, so far we found two things that make
people cheat more.
We found that the distance for money and
we found the social acceptance, kind of
seeing other people behave in egregious
way.
But we also wanted to find out what are
personality traits, which are the people
that would cheat more?
Now you could speculate a lot of things.
You can say maybe the people who are more
egocentric or maybe the people who are
more competitive, maybe the people hate
losing.
You can speculate on a lot of things, but
if you think about our theory.
Our theory is that people want to view
themselves as honest people and also want
to benefit from cheating.
We want to have the cake and eat it too.
We want both of those things.
Who are the people that could do that?
And what we thought was that maybe those
are creative people.
Because if it's all about rationalization,
if this kind of cheating we discover is
all about being able to cheat and
rationalize it, so it doesn't affect our
own image, people who are more creative
presumably can just tell better stories.
They can cheat more and rationalize it to
an even higher degree, so we tried that.
We tried to measure people creativity and
measure how much they cheat, and we found
that more creative people cheat more.
We tried to increase creativity with some
creativity enhancing exercises.
And we found that as we were increase
creativity slightly, we also got cheating
to increase slightly.
We also went to a big advertising agency,
and we checked the moral flexibility of
people in different jobs in that
advertising agency.
And we saw that as the job required more
creativity, people cheated more.
There was less cheating in accounting,
accounting much more cheating in the
creative professions.
And, you know, maybe it is good that
there's less cheating in accounting, but
it clearly supports this theory that our
version of cheating, it's all about this
rationalizing.
It's about acting badly and rationalizing,
and the question is to what extent can we
do it.
If we're multiple distance, multiple steps
removed from money, we can do it to a
higher degree.
If people around us are doing it more, we
can do it to a higher degree.
If we ourselves are better storytellers,
more creative storytellers, we can do it
to a higher degree.
All of those things are contributing to a
very high degree.
So what have we learned up to this point?
I think if we think about the Becker
model, that cheating is basically driven
by how much to I stand gain?
What's the probability of being caught?
What kind of punishment will I get?
And doing some cost benefit analysis.
That doesn't explain much of our behavior.
It's also not the case that we have bad
apples.
If you think about what is real cheating
due to?
In Enron, and other cases, is it due to
bad apples, or is it due to lots and lots
of people cheating a little bit?
I think it's much more due to lots and
lots of people, cheating a little bit.
And specifically we learned a few things
that either hinder it or increase it.
So we learned that getting people to think
more carefully about their morality
shrinks the fudge factor and gets people
to behave more honestly.
We also learned that it's all about
rationalization.
So, when we have something that is
multiple steps removed from money, we can
cheat more, and at the same time
rationalize it.
When you see other people around us
behaving in immoral ways, we can cheat a
bit more, and rationalizing it.
And when we ourselves are creative, we can
rationalize, we can tell better stories,
cheat more, and feel good about ourselves.
And I think that if we have this
perspective, it means we should not direct
much of our attention to the cost-benefit
analysis.
We should not think about something like,
how do we expose people, and how do we
punish them, and how do we, eh,
surveillance them?
Because all of those approaches are driven
to this idea that people are just doing
the cost-benefit analysis.
And if you say no, most of the cheating is
not about that, it's about what people can
feel comfortable with themselves.
Now we have to ask with different
approaches, how do we get people to be
comfortable with less cheating?
How do we get people to become aware of
their own traps?
How do we create rules that don't allow
this flexibility in terms of
rationalization?
And I think this will be the actual
Improvement.
You know, across all of our experiments,
we ran about 30,000 people, we found about
12 people that cheated a lot, and we lost
about $150 to these guys.
We found about 18,000 people who cheated
just a little bit, and we lost about
$36,000 to those people.
And I think that this is probably a good
reflection of what's happening in society.
Sure, there are bad apples.
There are people who steal, and so on.
And it's terrible.
But economically, it's a small potato,
these are small things in terms of
economic impact.
The big economic impact comes from lots of
people cheating a little bit, but because
there are so many of them the economic
impact is much higher.
And I don't think we need to stop thinking
about the crooks, but I think we need to
pay more attention to the people who can
change just a little bit and feel good
about themselves.
Now, I think if we do it, everybody would
be better off.