Hi, my name is David Pizzaro, I'm a
psychologist at Cornell University and I
study emotions, especially emotions and
how they influence judgement.
Today I want to talk to you about one of
those emotions, the emotion of disgust
and how it might influence your thinking
in surprising ways.
For a long time psychologists have
pointed to the power of emotions.
In fact emotions are those things that
motivate us toward action.
Many times these emotions are things that
motivate us toward actions that would
keep us alive.
For instance our strongest emotions,
emotions like fear are ones that keep us
from getting close to natural predators.
There's a reason why we're afraid
naturally of things like lions and snakes
and spiders.
But emotions don't only motivate us to
behave in certain ways like avoiding
predators.
They also seem to change the way we think
about the world.
That is when your'e fearful, not only do
you want to run from the lion, but you're
more likely to think that there are lions
everywhere.
And this influence on judgement has some
interesting effects.
What I want to talk to you about today is
the power that the emotion of disgust
might have on the way we make our
judgments.
And how a very natural emotion that keeps
us away from things that might
contaminate us or give us diseases also
changes the way we think about our
social, moral, political, and even our
consumer decisions.
Now, the insight that emotions could even
be studied systematically probably first
came from Charles Darwin.
Who wrote a book in the late 1800s
systematically documenting the universal
nature of many human emotions.
Psychologists in the 60s picked up this
original project of Darwin's and
documented that across the world there
appeared to be a set of universal basic
emotions and these as I said, are the
kinds of emotions that were, are around
and universal because they help us adapt
to our natural environment.
So for instance, we have fear, surprise,
disgust, anger.
All of these are there in the human
system, in the human mind, in the human
body because they give us a certain kind
of survival advantage.
Disgust is one of these basic universal
emotions.
That is no matter where you look, no
matter what culture you look to,
somebody, people seem to have this
natural adversive response to things that
are gross.
Things that might contaminate us or give
us diseases.
This is a good emotion.
It keeps our bodies clean, right, disease
is something that we've had to deal with
throughout most of human history.
So avoiding disease with this natural
program of disease avoidance, that we
might call disgust, is a very good thing.
You can see the origins of this even
early in infancy.
if you take a bitter liquid or sour
liquid and you put it into the mouth of
an infant, a newborn, what you'll see is
something very much like the full blown
adult disgust face.
They'll wrinkle up their nose.
They'll even protrude their tongue trying
to get that thing out of their mouth.
In fact when we make a disgust response,
even though we can't see that we're
sticking out our tongue, we're often
actually moving our tongue in that same
way.
So, one of the things that's very
interesting about disgust and actually
one of the reasons I started studying it
was because it's very, very easy to make
people disgusted.
Some of the other emotions are hard to
influence in the laboratory.
That is we can bring people in the lab
and we can try to make them angry.
We can try to make them afraid with
various methods.
But disgust we don't have to try very
hard.
I'm just going to give you one example of
a disgusting image I'll just prepare you
in advance that I'm about to show you
something disgusting.
Some of you might actually show that same
emotion face that I just showed you where
you wrinkle up your nose.
Right.
This is something that we might see in
any day in, in, in our lives but it's
something that probably has a profound
ability to make you feel disgust.
Some of you might feel it more than
others.
And in fact when we look at the sorts of
things that make us feel disgusted across
cultures we see a very common pattern.
As I said, these are things that tend to
make us sick if we touch them or come
into contact with them.
So things like feces, urine, blood,
vomit, rotten flesh, pus, all of those
things are universal triggers of disgust.
That is to say although we can override
them sometimes.
No matter where you look people seem to
respond with the same reaction.
And the, it makes sense.
These things are also things that might
actually make us sick.
They're signs of disease.
Now, when Darwin was investigating the
emotions, he wrote something that I think
was very insightful.
he says here in Tierra del Fuego, a
native touched with his finger some cold
preserved meat while I was eating and
plainly showed disgust at it's softness.
While I felt utter disgust at my food
being touched by a a naked savage, though
his hands did not appear dirty.
So one of the things that Darwin is
pointing out early on is that the same
disgust reaction that he has, he saw in
the savage.
This was an early documentation of the
universe, universal nature of disgust but
Darwin also points to something
interesting, that is, that we not only
feel disgust for things that might
contaminate us by putting it in our,
putting it in our mouth, or maybe by
touching it, but we also feel disgust
very easily at people, other people,
people that might be foreign from us.
And he also points to the fact that
disgust, one of the real important
features of disgust Is that it works
through contagion.
To give you an example, if you stand next
to a lion I might be afraid of the lion
but I'm not now afraid of you.
Disgust doesn't work that way.
If you touch something disgusting, now
that thing has the property of disgust.
That is, through this association with
the bad thing.
That has now been contaminated and I
don't want to touch it.
And if you think about it, this is a very
good thing if what we're trying to avoid
is disease.
So before we had an explicit theory of
how germs spread and cause disease, the
emotion of disgust was tracking
contagion.
The power of contagion is at work a lot
in, in the emotion of disgust.
Especially as we navigate our daily
social moral political lives.
but also when we make our consumer
decisions.
Let me give you an example from one
study.
researchers gave individuals a mug and
asked them, how much do you think this
mug is worth?
This was compared to a group who were
just asked, how much do you think this
mug is worth.
but we're not given the mug, and it turns
out in general people think that their
own, their own things are worth more.
So if you say how much would you sell
this mug for, how much is worth?
If I've just given it to you, you'd
actually think that it's worth more.
But if I showed you disgusting images
like the one I just showed you before,
that effect goes away.
One of the most robust effects, that we
like things and we value things that are
our own more than those things that
belong to others, can be completely wiped
out if we are now feeling disgust when
evaluating the value of our own product.
In another set of studies If products
that are disgusting touched products that
were not disgusting so in this case a
product that has to come into close
contact with the body.
They used tampons.
If tampons touched a bag of cookies, mind
you both of them were closed and they
were clean tampons.
There was no chance of any contamination
going on.
Just the fact that people were disgusted
slightly by the tampons made them value
the cookies less.
Now this property of contagion that we
can see in consumer decisions extends to
what might be considered a very a much
more important domain.
That is we can make you feel disgusted
not at cookies or a mug, we can make you
feel disgusted about a person or an
entire social group.
This has been used quite effectively and
quite tragically in many cases.
One of the best cases comes from World
War 2 propaganda, where the Germans were
trying to convince people that the, that
the Jews were filthy, disgusting
individuals in, in part to make it easier
to kill them.
So, this comes, this quote comes from a
Nazi children's book published in 1938.
Trying to point the children to the
disgusting, the disgusting features of
Jewish people.
It says just look at these guys!
The louse-infested beards!
The filthy, protruding ears, those
stained fatty clothes.
Jews often have an unpleasant sweetish
odor.
If you have a good nose you can smell the
Jews.
More recently this very same tactic has
been used by people who want to convince
us that homosexuality is bad or immoral.
So this is taken from an anti-gay
website, gays are worthy of death for
their vile sex practices, they're like
dogs eating their own vomit and sows
wallowing in their own feces.
Again, these very low level discussed
properties, pointing to human bodily
products for instance or, or specific
descriptions of sexual acts get the
disgust reaction going, and through the
process of contagion, we tag an
individual or an entire social group, and
it gives us a very, very strong avoidance
and negative response to that group.
Now, one of the questions that my
colleagues and I wanted to answer was are
some people just more prone, more
susceptible, to being convinced by this
process of contagion.
And so, one of the things that we wanted
to look at was, well, maybe some people
who are more easy to disgust than others
would be more likely to have some kind of
negative attitudes toward certain social
groups.
And we were able to do that by looking
across the population at, simply put, the
levels of squeamishness that individuals
have.
Just as with many other basic universal
notions, while we all have them, some of
them have them much stronger than others.
So in this class, there are many of you
who when I showed that image had a very,
very strong response, some of you weren't
even bothered at all and wondered why I
bothered to put the picture up.
We can actually measure this level of
squeamishness using a scale called the
disgust sensitivity scale and plot people
along the line of how easily disgusted
they are in everyday life and how hard to
disgust they are.
we do this by asking a series of
questions.
Let me give you a couple of examples.
Imagine that you were asked this.
Even if I were hungry I would not drink a
bowl of my favorite soup if it had been
stirred by a used but thoroughly washed
fly swatter.
How much do you agree or disagree with
that statement?
Or, while you're walking through a tunnel
under a railroad track, you smell urine.
Would you be very disgusted or not at all
disgusted at?
It turns out that I'm actually very very
disgusted so it's hard for me to do this
research.
But we can plot a score given enough of
these questions that gives you an overall
score on how discussed sensitive you are,
how squeamish you are.
One of the things that this can do is
predict your actual behavior.
So the researchers that came up with the
scale brought people into the laboratory
and asked them to do a variety of tasks
that were disgusting.
For instance, eat perfectly healthy, in
fact very nutritious, meal worms but that
nobody eats worms really in the United
States so they were very disgusting.
or something milder like eat a piece of
chocolate that's been baked to look like
a, to look like dog poop.
it turns out people find, people who are
very easily disgusted are much less
likely to do that than people who are not
easily disgusted.
So your score on this scale actually
predicts your actual disgust response and
your behavior.
One of the first things we found was that
disgust sensitivity, that is level of
squeamishness, seems to predict of all
things, political orientation.
As people who are more likely to be
politically conservative were also more
likely to say they were easily disgusted.
Another way of saying this though, is
that people who report being more liberal
are less easy to disgust.
You might imagine why one way or the
other might make more sense.
But this is the general relationship.
And we found this over three, four, five
different data collections looking at
different populations.
Until we finally came to a very very big
data set at least when speaking about
psychology, we were able to look at
nearly 30,000 respondents in the United
States, what you see on this graph is
that people who are very conservative
there on the right, are much more likely
to report that they are easily disgusted.
That's higher numbers there indicate
their more squeamish.
And on the other hand, people were very
liberal or actually less likely to be
easily disgusted..
We found this even though we were able to
statically control for a variety of
factors that we know are related both to
disgust sensitivity and to political
orientation like socioeconomic status,
income, education levels, religiosity
even some of the biggest personality
traits that we know are associated with
both.
No matter what we still found a general
relationship between disgust sensitivity
how easily disgusted you are and your
political beliefs.
And this actually predicted not just how
you respond on a one to seven scale of
how politically conservative you are or
liberal, but it also seemed to predict
actually voting behavior.
That is when we look at state by state
voting results in the 2008 US
presidential election, what we found was
that levels of disgust sensitivity in a
state predicted the margin of victory of
Obama over McCain.
That is, states that had, in general,
higher levels of discussed sensitivity.
Where, states where McCain actually got
more votes compared to Obama.
Now, we were wondering whether this was
maybe just a feature of American
politics.
So, we looked across the world.
Across 121 different countries.
Here, you see collapsed into a number of
geographical regions.
We ask the same kinds of political
questions and discuss sensitivity
questions.
And what we were able to see was these
numbers indicate the strength of the
relationship the correlation between
discuss sensitivity and political
orientation.
What you see is no matter where you look
across the world the samae result
emerges.
That is by enlarged the more likely you
are to be easily disgusted the more
likely you are to be politically
conservative.
Or again you are liberal if you are not
usually discussed it.
Now this is a fairly small effect this
accounts for a small part of why we might
have political beliefs.
But nonetheless it's interesting because
most people might not think that how
easily disgusted they are by things like
on flush toilets or speak to strangers
soda.
Might actually predict who they vote for
in a presidential election.
One of the questions that we had was
whether we could actually shift people's
attitudes towards social groups and moral
and political attitudes in particular by
making them disgusted.
So what we did at Cornell in our lab was
bring participants into the lab.
And asked them to fill out a series of
questionnaires.
In this particular study we asked them to
evaluate certain social groups.
We knew that there was a strong link
between homosexuality and disgust.
Because of the way that many people who
are anti homosexual talk about the sex
act and use disgust in order to convince
people.
So we wanted to see if if making people
disgusted in a completely unrelated way.
That is we weren't making them disgusted
about sex or anything like that.
We were making them disgusted with a
fould odor.
Essentially we sprayed with a really
nasty odor on every other day, and we
brought participants into the lab, and
asked them what they thought about
certain social groups.
African-Americans, the elderly,
immigrants, gay men, and lesbian women.
And what we found was, that the foul odor
had a particularly strong effect In fact,
the only effect we found, was that it
made people negatively evaluate gay men
more.
So that is, on the days when people had
to evaluate gay men, where there was a
foul smell in the room, they were more
likely to find, to report greater
negative attitudes.
Here, this is plotting on a feeling
thermometer.
That is, from zero to 100, how warmly, or
coldly, do you feel toward gay men.
Other labs have also looked at these
differences using physiological measures,
you might wonder self report, that is if
you ask, if I ask you how easily
disgusted you are, maybe you're not so
accurate.
But if I hook you up to physiological
measures, measures of heart beat, and
skin conductance that we know are rough
measures of arrousal, and show you
disgusting images We find the same
general effect.
People who report being greater
conservatives, more likely to be
politically conservative, are more
physiologically aroused when presented
with disgusting images.
Liberals are less physically aroused.
In particular, attitudes towards
homosexuality and abortion were the ones
that predicted more, most, whether or not
people would be aroused by disgusting
images that had nothing to do with those
issues such as dog feces.
Well, there's another way to kick in this
feeling that there might be contamination
in the environment.
So discussed is a particularly powerful
way to do this, but discussed again, is
in the service of keeping us from getting
sick.
You can show similar effects by just
reminding people that there is disease
prevelant in the environment.
And a number of researchers have used
this disease avoidance As a manipulation.
We thought, well, perhaps just reminding
people that there's contamination in the
environment might get them to change
their political and moral attitudes.
So, we conducted a study where all we did
was remind people that the swine flu was,
was prevalent in Cornell and that they
should sanitize their hands.
In one case we explicitly told them that
they should sanitize their hands.
And asked them a number of, of questions
about their moral beliefs and their
political beliefs.
In another case we actually just asked
them to fill out a questionnaire, either
next to a hand sanitizing station or not.
And what we found is, was that a simple
reminder to wash your hands actually had
a pretty strong effect on your moral
beliefs.
In this case beliefs about sexually weird
but harmless practices.
Let me give you an example.
so we asked people, imagine that Joe is
house sitting for his grandmother and Joe
invites his girlfriend over and they have
sex on his grandmother's bed.
Now, if I'd just reminded you that you
should wash your hands because of the
swine flu, you're more likely to find
that to be morally wrong that if I had to
be.
When we asked people to report their
political orientation in their same set
of studies we also found general effect
that simply reminding people to wash
their hands had a change in how
conservative there reported being
politically conservative.
So a simple reminder of of disgust or of
contamination can change our consumer
decisions.
It can change our political decisions, it
can change our moral decisions.
This is a case in which disgust is not
simply preventing us from eating things
that might make us sick but it's having a
fairly profound influence on our social,
political, moral judgements.
The question that I want to leave you
with is now that we know this, we can
finally get to the point where we can ask
when should emotions influence our
thinking?
Science isn't particularly well-suited to
answer this question.
All we can do is point out how emotions
work.
How emotions can influence the way we
make decisions and judgements.
But we have to now ask the additional
question, now that we know that, should
disgust shape the way, for instance, you
will.
Who you vote for in the political, in the
political elections, what you vote for
about gay rights, or what you buy at the
grocery store.
Thank you very much.