[music] Hello, hello.
I'm Aline.
That was funny because Dan says hello,
hello.
You probably don't know that yet, but you
will learn over the course of this course.
>> And I'm Susan.
>> And we're going to show you how to get
around this website.
>> To get to the home tab, you click on
the upper left on the big tab that says
home.
That will fill in as the course progresses
with announcements like these, videos and
other things that you'll see as the course
progresses.
On the right side your going to see fill
in with quizzes and other upcoming
assignments to let you know what is going
on this week.
>> Just below home you'll find the video
lectures.
You may have even found this video there.
The video lectures are going to be
separated by topic and week.
So every week has it's own topic.
As you can see here, week one, we're going
to cover rationality, week two, we'll look
at the psychology of money, week three, is
all about dishonesty, week four, we get to
labor and motivation, week five, is all
about self control, and week six is
emotion.
These videos build on each other, so
you're probably going to want to watch
them in succession, and you can't really
skip ahead because we're only going to
post them one week at a time.
We have some special guest lecturers, so
every week you'll hear a bit about
different topics, and these will hopefully
add to Dan's perspective on the topic of
that week.
You can also download these videos if you
have a slow internet connection or you
just want to take it with you wherever you
go, and show your friends and family.
There are subtitles as well although it
may be a little harder to understand with
the subtitles given the Dan-speak and your
brain can more easily process information
when, when you translate it automatically
into human English.
Now we also have the ability to speed up
videos.
So, if you're in a rush, you want to watch
something in, 1.5 time.
Unfortunately we can't do double time, but
1.5 is just as good.
Then you can do that as well.
Next we have the reading assignments, just
below the video lectures.
Here, you'll find both the required and
the recommended readings.
The required readings are going to be on
the quizzes, if you decide to take the
quizzes.
Which we hope you do because actually they
are pretty amusing, according to me and
Susan.
And these are really meant to get you to
think, to question their findings outside
of what they're given at face value.
And by doing so, reading through that and
you can learn a bit about how research in
behavioral economics is done, and also
just start thinking more like a scientist.
>> Quizzes are the next tab down.
We have 2 types of quizzes for this
course.
Although in the lecture you'll also be
getting quizzes, those are just there to
make sure you haven't fallen asleep.
The first type of quiz that you're going
to be taking is based on lecture.
The second type is based on the required
readings for each weeks and you'll be able
to find those under readings.
That's it, pretty self explanatory.
>> Now we've come to the discussion for a
yes, I said fora not forums.
This is where you'll have the most
interaction with your fellow students.
There's place for everything on the
discussion boards, introductions,
lectures, assignments, study groups,
feedback and there is even a place for
things that don't have a place.
So, if you have a question about one of
the readings or the lectures, if you're
having technical difficulties or even if
just want to say, hey.
This is the place to do it.
>> The main point we want to make about
the discussion boards is that they need to
be self-sustaining.
As much as Aline and I would like to be
there all the time, we can't monitor these
24, 7.
So, when you have a question, search for
it and highlight it.
The key is to help out your peers and most
of all, be nice.
Nobody likes a troll.
>> One crucial feature of the discussion
fora is their role in shaping Dan's weekly
office hours.
So every week, we'll take your questions
and your discussion points and we'll pose
our favorite ones to Dan, and he'll
respond.
We'll post that video online, and you can
see his answers to all sorts of questions
that you come up with.
To submit a question for office hours, all
you need to do is add the office hours tag
to your post.
This literally mean that all you have to
do is type office hours in the tag base.
>> We have one short writing assignment in
this course and you'll see it in the tab
to the left labeled writing assignment.
If you choose to do this and we highly
recommend that you do.
You won't just be a writer, you will also
be a grader.
It's impossible for the two of us to grade
all of your essays, and we have no way of
automatically doing it.
So we're relying on you to make this work.
Fortunately we know from other courses
that people seem to enjoy both aspects of
this, both the writing and the grading.
>> You might also see a button that says,
Don't Click Here.
What's that all about?
Looks dangerous.
You probably don't want to click that.
>> Next are the Abouts which give you all
sorts of information of this course.
Within the, About this course section, is
a lot more information that you'll want to
go over.
First is the description section which has
an overview of the course.
Next, is the format which has more
information about finding your way around
the site and what to do once you're on a
tab.
Next is the Timeline which has our
schedule.
Then the Assignments and Assessments which
has more about grading.
And finally we have a section on Dan And
You and that tells you how to relate and
communicate with the course staff.
There are lots of you.
Please don't email us, we can't handle it.
Please use the discussion fora.
>> In the second about, you can learn all
about us.
Not just Dan, but Susan and myself and our
TA's.
I guess that makes them TAA's?
But really, there's a pretty remarkable
crew behind this entire course, from
designing the videos to designing the
site.
And, you know, I'm not even going to get
into it.
[laugh] Everyone deserves a shout out, and
you should give them some props because
they're awesome.
>> The third and last About is all about
you.
Because this class is offered
internationally, we have students from all
over the world, and we really like for you
all to be represented on a map.
To make sure that happens, please fill out
the initial survey that we've emailed to
all of you so that we can get your
location data and put you all up on a map.
>> Now, for some super fun features of
this class, the course Wiki is another
place for you to learn cool things and
make your mark.
We've set it up for you with a bunch of
awesome contents, links to outside sources
and some videos and even some other
articles.
And there's a glossary that will be super
helpful for you if you don't understand
what, you know, hedonic calculus is, or
Dan throws in some, some terms in his
lectures that you just don't quite get
right away, refer to the glossary, we've
dumped a bunch of things there for you to,
to help you out.
But really this, this is a place for you
to add, your own character for you to put
in things that excite you and you think
are relevant to the course.
So of course this will change over time,
but let's look at the Wiki as it is now.
It's divided into the weekly topics of the
course, so you see we have the main page
with all the topics and some more fun
stuff down here.
But really, you should explore, have fun.
>> Finally, the last tab on your left, is
the meet up tab.
Meet up is a great tool for coursera, it
allows you to arrange to meet people in
person.
For anything from reading groups to Nerdy
behavior like[UNKNOWN] parties, you can
dress up as your favorite social
scientist.
>> That's it for the site tour.
You probably could have learned just as
much by clicking around, but hopefully you
enjoyed yourself and got to know us a
little better in the process.
And just remember, we're here for you.
Chicka, chicka.
>> [inaudible].
>> Learn cool things guys.