Hi, my name's Gavan Fitzsimons.
I'm the R.
David Thomas professor of marketing and
psychology here at Duke University.
today I'm going to be taking a little
time to tell you about some of the work
we do in our lab.
focused around an issue that we like to
call the unconscious consumer.
And usually when I say the term
unconscious consumer in one sort of,
package like that, it starts to make
people a little bit nervous.
And I say, wait a second, I'm not
unconscious when I'm in consumption mode.
When I'm walking through a store, I know
exactly what I'm doing.
But I'm choosing between two autombiles,
I know exactly what I'm doing.
When I'm deciding whether to have that
snack or take a pass, I know exactly what
I'm doing.
In fact, what I'm going to do today is
try to convince you that far more is
occurring outside your conscious
awareness than you'd like to believe when
you're in consumption mode.
I thought I'd start out, I had sort of
three little ideals that I'd like tell
you about, but I though I'd start out
with a personal anecdote.
This is going back a little ways, to when
I was a graduate student myself.
I was I was living New York at the time,
I was a graduate student at Columbia.
And, it was a January night, it was maybe
40ish degrees Fahrenheit, 2 or 3 Celsius
and it was kind of drizzly and rainy out.
I realized had I ran out of Diet Coke.
This was quite a tragedy for me.
I love Diet Coke.
I needed to fill my fridge with Diet Coke
immediately.
So I was in short, soccer shorts, and a
t-shirt and flip-flops.
Fortunately in living in Manhattan theirs
a deli sort of underneath every building.
To get to my deli, I had to go out the
front door, around the corner into the
deli.
And so out I went, money in hand, ready
to purchase my 2 liter diet coke.
Walked into the deli, nodded hi to the
guy behind the counter, went over to the
spot where the 2 liter Diet Coke was.
But there was no 2 liter Diet Coke.
I was taken aback.
Empty spot where the 2 liter Diet Coke
always was.
So I leaned back to the fella behind the
counter.
I said, hey, can you grab a couple of, 2
liter Diet Cokes?
And he said, I can still hear his accent
and everything in my mind.
He said, I'm sorry.
We're all out of 2 liter Diet Coke.
Nothing could have been more horrible to
me at the time.
I love my Diet Coke and I love my 2 liter
Diet Coke.
He followed up with an interesting
statement, which was, I'll give you 2
1-liter bottles of diet coke for the same
price as a 2 liter bottle.
I paused for a moment.
I thought about it and I realized I
didn't want 2 1-liter bottles of diet
coke, I wanted a 2 liter bottle of diet
coke.
So I left in a little bit of a huff,
walked out of the deli, walked up the
street.
Now, I think I mentioned, it was quite
chilly and raining.
I get up the block, go into the next
deli.
In New York there's a deli every block.
went into the next deli, looked, no 2
liter diet coke.
Went out another block, another deli, no
2 liter diet coke.
At this point, I had a decision.
Do I give up?
Do I walk the whole way across the avenue
which is maybe a quarter mile, a half a
kilometer, something like that, to a dip,
to another deli.
I did so, I got there, walked in.
They had 2 liter Diet Coke, fantastic.
I bought 6 bottles of it.
Now I had 6 bottles, 3 in each hand.
Walking back across Columbia campus,
soaking wet, freezing cold.
Arms pulling out of their shoulder
sockets and I realized, something bizarre
has just happened to me.
What was it?
I was experiencing something that folks
have called psychological reactance, and
reactance is the, basically the idea
that, when something's restricted, when
freedom of my choice is restricted, I'm
going to fight really hard to get it
back.
In that particular instance, it was the
first personal anecdotal experience I'd
ever had of a psychological process
overpowering me, taking over my actions,
leading to some, somewhat [LAUGH] strange
consumption behavior all outside of my
conscious awareness and control.
And, that sort of triggered this notion
of for me, of understanding forces that
occur outside our conscious control, that
might be shaping our consumption
behavior.
one of the interesting follow ups from
that, sort of basic observation and line
of work we did, was realizing that
oftentimes the trigger for a restriction
of a freedom aren't nearly as obvious to
you as the lack of a 2 liter Diet Coke in
it's spot in the store.
So for example in a social domain we
found that, and this is work with Amy
Dalton and Tanya Chartrand.
Tanya, who happens to be my wife once
observed that I often don't do the things
that she would like me to do and I
expressed surprise at that observation on
her part, and we ended up doing some
research on the topic.
And what we found was that there are
certain people who chronically experience
this notion of resistance to
restrictions, on an automatic basis.
And I actually, what we found was that
myself and people like me that don't like
to have their freedoms restricted will
actually restrict or will react against
what their significant others would like
them to do.
Your mom, your dad, your loved one, they
would like you to say, work hard, for
example.
Alright, all it takes for some folks is
to hear in the way background, the little
background back there, the name of their
significant other.
The name of their mom or dad.
Instead of actually doing the things that
their mom or dad or loved one would like
you to do, like work hard.
You actually do the exact opposite.
Completely outside conscious awareness
sometimes.
It's such a strong effect that we were
able to subliminally prime, and
subliminal is Latin for sub, meaning
below and liminal meaning threshold so
below threshold.
Subliminally prime people with the name
of their loved one.
So much so that, or below their level of
awareness so we prime them below their
level of awareness.
So in a way that their sort of optical
system and their brain can recognize the
name of the significant other, but at a
conscious level they are not able to do
so.
so we activate in their minds the name of
this significant other and then we put
them in this situation where they could
work hard or relax.
For many people that experience
psychological reactants on a regular
bases.
They actually backlashed against what
their loved one wanted them to do, and
did the exact opposite.
Back into a consumption setting, we take
that same kind of notion.
So now, some of us are, are sort of,
bristle at restrictions, don't like
people to tell us what to do.
Some of you that are, are watching this
today might think to yourself, well I can
sort of identify with that, I've about
had it with people telling me what to do
in certain spaces.
So, some of you might have heard recently
that you should, for example, eat
healthy.
And I bet if you've heard eat healthy
once you've heard eat healthy a thousand
times.
Or exercise.
You should exercise more, right.
And again if you've heard it once, you've
heard it a thousand times.
As you repeatedly get exposed to those
message in your life, for some of us, we
build up a resistance to that message.
And in fact, we want to do just the
opposite of that.
And that was sort of the underlying
premise of some work that Peggie Lou,
who's a PhD student with with me, started
doing, looking at what we call indirect
priming, or indirect persuasion.
And so the idea here is that by
sometimes, we're better to indirectly try
to reach out to a person to a consumer
and try to pursued them to do something
that might be in their best interest by
not triggering this backlash reaction.
And so for example if we want you to eat
healthy we have found that it's actually
better to subliminally prime you with the
message exercise, rather, then
subliminally with the message eat
healthy.
If we subliminally prime you with the
message eat healthy, some people will
actually not eat healthy, they'll
backlash against it.
And, and so we find that these indirect
means to try to persuade folks, can
sometimes be more effective then a direct
in your face kind of message.
So, when your thinking about trying to
eat healthy, when your thinking about
trying to exercise in your own sort of
lives think about what are the triggers
in this environment that might lead me to
outside of my conscience awareness
actually back lash against this message
and do something that in the long run
could actually quite be harmful to me.
so those are little examples of this idea
that we can backlash against situational,
environmental cues, in consumption ways,
that will actually lead to outcomes that
can be bad for us.
obviously, if you sort of think
classically from a, a traditional
decision making, a traditional economic
perspective, we would never do something
that would be bad for us.
And I think most folks, if you asked
them, would not want to engage in these
negative behaviors.
And yet, we find ourselves doing so.
And I'll return and, and, and visit to
this general idea that sometimes things
occur outside conscious awareness that
might not be so good for us in, in a bit.
the second line of work that I thought
would be fun to, to talk about today is
some work that we've done looking at,
what we call, brief brand exposures.
And the ideal here is that we're exposed,
the average consumer is exposed to many
many brands in a paticular, in one day.
So for example, most western societies,
we're exposed to somewhere between 5 and
10,000 brands in a day.
And obviously that's far too many brands
for us to consciously process in a
meaningful way.
so what happens?
Does this simply, do they simply pass in
front of us, a logo on someones shirt a
thing on a co-, on a coffee cup.
or are they affecting us in some way, are
they simply, you know, background noise
or are they affecting us in some way?
And one of the, the studies that we did
to try to to sort of understand this this
question, or to answer this question, was
a study with with Tanya Chartrand and
[UNKNOWN] Fitzsimmons where we looked at
at different brief brand exposures.
And the two that we'll tell you about
today is Apple and IBM.
So, we choose two brands that are in the
product category, we then subliminally
exposed people to one of each of these
two brands.
And, we then looked to see if it had an
effect on peoples behavior in some
meaningful way.
the domain that we looked at to test
whether it was impacting behavior, was in
the, the sort of field of creativity.
And the ideal was, that the Apple brand
logo had very strong associations with
creativity.
Both Apple and IBM were equally liked,
they were equally well-known, etcetera.
but Apple had a really strong set of
associations with creativity.
So we exposed people to the brand logos
outside their conscious awareness, and we
put them in a setting where they could be
creative, where they could demonstrate
creativity.
And what we found, was that people
exposed to the Apple brand logo were
dramatically more creative than people
exposed to the Apple or to the IBM logo.
Apple exposed people way more creative,
IBM exposed people slightly less creative
than a neutral of situation in the
middle.
So here's a, there's a little example of
the simple incidental brand exposures
that occur on a daily basis, thousands of
them.
And each of them is impacting us
potentially in some way changing our
behavior.
Now, if I asked you do you think you be
got more creative because you saw that
Apple logo.
I'm certain that everybody watching today
would say, no that seems crazy.
That really seems silly.
How can that possibly be the case?
and yet, we have very clear empirical
evidence that these brief exposures
change both the psychological process, as
well as actual behavior.
So, I've talked to you today about
backlash, and how backlash can occur
outside our conscious awareness,
sometimes leading to harmful effects.
I've talked to you about brief brand
exposures, IBM and Apple, that can lead
to positive effects.
When should be we terrified that we're
being influenced outside our conscious
awareness, left, right, and center.
I think it's easy to become paranoid that
that the world around you is trying to
change your behavior.
The truth of the matter is the world
around you is trying to change your
behavior.
Some of it is very systematic, some of it
is not.
I like to tell people when they think
about unconscious consumption, that it's
typically not the case that, for example,
subliminal exposure to any kind of brand
logo will make you choose that brand
logo.
So for example I'm a Diet Coke drinker, I
love my Diet Coke.
You could expose me to Diet Pepsi a
million times in a row.
I'll never choose Diet Pepsi over Diet
Coke.
Alright, however, with exposure to Diet
Coke, whether it be through an ad,
through watching someone walk by on a
street with a Diet Coke lead me to want
to consume a little more Diet Coke?
The answer is proablay yes.
So if you're trying to defend against
that we've got to be very vigilant,
alright.
The reality is though that our ability to
defend against the non-conscience
influence in our environments is pretty
limited.
So I like to say and I like to, I'd like
to leave you with this thought that it's
probably worthwhile investing in being
strategic about the brands and the
consumption objects you surround yourself
with.
So, for example, if you're a swimmer, and
you'd like to really swim a faster race,
you'd like to cut a couple of tenths off
your 50 meter swim.
Maybe you should wear the same parka, on
the warm up deck, that Michael Phelps
wore.
Now, the first day that you buy that
parka, and you put it on, you're going to
feel silly.
You're going to realize that you've got
Michael Phelps' parka on, and clearly
that can't make you a faster swimmer.
The second day, you might still feel a
little of that.
3 weeks out, you're not going to be
consciously thinking about the fact that
you're strategically donning Michael
Phelps' warm-up jacket.
But that association between the jacket
and Michael Phelps and how fast a swimmer
he is, is going to be activated at some
level below your conscious threshold in
your mind.
You hit the pool, you swim, you cut the 2
10ths off.
Same thing for creativity, for, for for
intelligence, for just about any
desirable aspirational goal you might
have.
Surrounding yourself with consumer goods
that are strongly associated with that
and activate that idea in your mind can
lead you to to basically be a, a
successful strategic user of brands,
products, etc.
Rather than letting you have brands,
products, etc, change you are, who you
are and, and, and the way that you behave
in a sort of random way.
So think strategically, surround yourself
with objects, with the brands, with the
products that are going to make you a
strategic unconscious consumer.