My name is Eli Finkel, I'm a professor of
psychology at Northwestern University.
And I'll be presenting some research that
has been spearheaded by Paul Eastwick, a
former graduate student of mine who is
now a professor at Texas, at University
of Texas.
And the title of the talk is the delusion
of romantic self-insight.
And I want to talk about how dating has
changed in the Internet era, and in
particular, I want to talk about online
dating.
One of the major assumptions of online
dating is that we can look at profiles of
potential romantic partners and discern
from reading those profiles who is
romantically compatible with us.
So, if that's true, that we have insight
into our preferences, and can tell who's
compatible with us, then this is an
outstanding way that we could go about
selecting our romantic partner or at
least reducing the size of the pool.
But if it's not true that we have insight
into our romantic preferences, then not
only are we wasting a great deal of time
by browsing all these profiles, but we
are also limiting or ruling out people
from the dating pool who might be
especially compatible with us.
And so, what I'll do today is talk about
the degree to which we have accurate
insight into our romantic preferences and
this question boils down to two distinct
questions.
The, the first one is, are there sex
differences in what people are looking
for in a potential romantic partner?
And, and the short answer to that is of
course there are.
Men are especially interested in looks,
much more then women are.
Women are especially interested in
earning prospects, more then men are.
Those are widely replicated sex
differences.
I want to probe a little deeper and find
out whether those sex differences hold up
when it really matters.
And the second question I have doesn't
involve sex differences.
It says, we as individuals, to what
degree do we have accurate insight into
what it is that tends to inspire our
romantic attraction?
If we do have good insight, then browsing
profiles is a great way to go about
finding a partner.
If we don't, then we really should
probably meet face-to-face to get a
chemistry check of who's compatible with
us.
Let's start by talking about sex
differences.
There are large sex differences in stated
preferences, that is, if you ask people
to what degree do you value a certain
series of characteristics, many things
men and women agree on, we all like warm
partners kind partners, etcetera.
But there are two massive sex differences
that I mentioned earlier.
The first is physical attractiveness, men
like that more than women, the second is
earning prospects, women like that more
than men.
But, before we conclude that these sex
differences are totally universal, let's
first examine a little bit about the
research paradigms that people have used
to try to establish those effects.
One of the major research programs or
research paradigms is to ask people about
hypothetical partners.
Specifically, ask them to what degree are
you looking for somebody who posses
characteristics like good earning
prospects or a good earning potential.
And you see the sex differences there,
men want looks more than women do, women
want earning prospects more than men do.
A second paradigm as you look at the
effects of physical attractiveness in
people depicted in photographs.
So when you're evaluating photographs,
men are more inspired by the attractive,
relative to the unattractive women more
than, more than women are attracted to
the, attractive versus the unattractive
men.
And the best research looks at personal
ads or online dating profiles, and
specifically, what we see in those is
that men tend to advertise things about
themselves oriented toward demonstrating
their earning prospects, women tend to
accentuate things related to their
physical attractiveness.
And when men and women respond to
personal ads or online dating profiles,
they tend to be differentially influenced
in a way that's consistent with all those
other sex differences.
But I have a question, what about after
men and women have actually met a
significant other, a another person
face-to-face, right?
Do these sex differences that hold up so
well in all those paradigms we've
discussed already, continue to hold up
once you've met an actual flesh and blood
person?
Well, one empirical approach, one method
that we can use to start unpacking that
question is speed dating.
And so, Paul Eastwick and I at
Northwestern University, ran a whole
series of speed dating events.
I, in fact, served as MC of these events.
And the way speed dating works is, is
these were heterosexual events we had 12
men and 12 women attend each event.
So if you're a man, you would go on a
4-minute date with each woman and then
the MC, I in this case, would blow a
whistle and you would rotate to the next
person.
Alright, so the way it works is that all
of the men went on 4-minute dates with
all the women, all the women, of course,
went on 4-minute dates with all of the
men.
And what we were able to do with this
method is we were able to look at the
degree to which physical attractiveness
and earning prospects actually predict
romantic attraction to flesh and blood
partners you have met in person.
And one of the things we wanted to do is
establish from the very outset that are,
that there was nothing strange about our
sample of participants.
So before they attended the speed dating
event, they reported about a week earlier
on their preferences, the standard, sorts
of measures that people regularly use.
To what degree are you interested in
somebody, to what degree is it important
to you that a potential partner is
good-looking or has good earning
prospects or is highly personable and
kind and warm?
And as you can see here in the graph men
care more than women about physical
attractiveness.
Again, this is on the, the questionnaire
that our speed daters completed the week
before they attended the lab session, the
speed, the speed dating even rather.
Women cared more about earning prospects
than men do.
And men and woman, as has been shown in
previous research, care about, equally
about how warm and kind a potential
partner is.
So here we are replicating the, the same
effects that everybody else replicates,
except we wanted to do something
different.
We wanted to take these same people, who
showed these standard sex differences,
and then introduce them to flesh and
blood partners through the speed dating
event.
And here, in this graph, you're going to
see some different information.
What you see on the y-axis is you see the
correlation of, of, of an attribute, the
physical attractiveness for example, with
attraction, right?
And so the idea should be that the more
the higher the correlation that you're
going to see here, means the more
strongly that characteristic iInspires
romantic attraction to the person.
And what you can see is, here are the
effects for physical attractiveness,
correlation is in about the 0.4 range,
but no sex difference.
The degree to which romantic physical
attractiveness inspires your romantic
attraction is equally strong regardless
of whether you're a man or a woman.
Now, let's turn to earning prospects.
Here, you can see that in general,
earning prospects are a little bit less
important in this sample than than
physical attractiveness is, the
correlations are in the, you know, 0.2
range.
But, what you can see is, once again, the
correlations are equally strong for men
and women.
None of these correlations was anywhere
close to statistic, statistically
significant.
And personable is also pretty attractive,
somewhere in between physically
attractive and earning prospects, and
once again, no sex difference.
Now, you might think, I hear you
thinking, right, so come on that's just
one study.
This is a very surprising effect.
Could it really be the case that men and
women don't actually have different
preferences for physical attractiveness
or earning prospects once they meet a
flesh and blood partner?
So what we wanted to do is we, we wanted
to conduct a meta-analysis, and
specifically, what that means Is we track
down every single published and
unpublished article that has looked at
people who have met face-to-face with a
potential partner and reported on that
partner how attracted they are or how
satisfied they are.
This also includes not only initial
attraction, but also in your marriage,
how satisfied are you and committed are
you to the marriage, etcetera.
But they have to report on a specific
person they've met face-to-face, not on
some hypothetical person who might be an
ideal partner for them.
The dependent variable that I was
suggesting earlier is, is an amalgam, a
combined sort of measure, right?
So, in an initial attraction context,
it's things like romantic liking, or
attraction, or sexual desire.
In marriage, for example, you'll see
things like relationship satisfaction or
how much you love your partner, etcetera.
And study, the other criterion we needed
to include studies in this meta-analysis,
include articles in this meta-analysis,
was that it had to have some measure of
physical attractiveness, earning
prospects, or both.
And some of these measures are the
participant's report.
So if I'm reporting how attracted I am to
you or how satisfied I am in our
marriage, then it could be my report of
how good-looking you are or my report of
your earning prospects.
It could be your report, so how
good-looking do you think you are or how
good, how promising you think your
earning prospects are or it could be an
objective assessment.
For example a consensus rating of a
photograph of you in terms of how
attractive you are or a measure of how,
what your actual income is, right?
So we, we look at all of those different
types of measures.
Now, for physical attractiveness, we were
able to find 73 articles with a total of
28,000 participants.
For earning prospects, we were able to
track down 44 articles with about 46,000
participants.
So, these are large samples, they really
put us in a good position to test, is
there a difference between men and women
and their earning prospects and can we
detect a statistically significant
difference?
We've got a lot of ability to do that in
a sample this large.
And what you see here, again, on the left
side of this graph is physical
attractiveness, on the right side, you
see earning prospects and once again, you
see nothing close to a statistically
significant difference.
So again, the take home message, not only
from the speed dating work at
Northwestern, but from the full corpus of
evidence that exists anywhere in the
world on this topic.
That physical attractiveness, big
correlate of how attractive you are to
people, big correlate of how happy you
are in your marriage, but not
differentially for men and women.
Earning prospects, a less significant
predictor of initial attraction and
satisfaction in your marriage, but once
again, not different for men and women.
Now, this raises a different set of
questions, right?
So the first set of questions were, well,
are there really sex differences in these
things that we assume to be sex
differentiated?
And the evidence now appears to be
overwhelming that there are not sex
differences in those mate preferences
once you meet a flesh and blood partner.
Now, the question is, well, what's going
on?
If those same people who reported a week
ago that they really cared a lot about
earning prospects and they cared less
about physical attractiveness, then a
week later meet a series of people in the
flesh and blood, a series of speed dating
partners, for example.
And they don't show those sorts of sex
differences that exhibited, that they
exhibited a week earlier, there's an
interesting question that emerges from
that, which is do people really know what
they want in the first place?
And this harken, harkens back, of course,
to the online dating question, the
profile browsing question.
So, ignoring sex differences, do people
who believe they value a certain
characteristic actually prize it more
than other people do?
And so, what we wanted to look at here is
the, the correspondence between what you
said you cared about in a romantic
partner, a week ago, and the degree to
which that characteristic actually
inspires your attraction once you meet
face-to-face.
And, if you look here in the, in this
first graph on the upper left, what you
see is how physically attractive the
partner is that you're rating.
And this black line represents people
who, who said that physical
attractiveness was extremely important to
them.
So, you can imagine, people vary in the
degree to which they say physical
attractiveness is important, these are
people who said, yes, it's extremely
important to me.
And not surprisingly, you see a strong
positive correlation such that as the
person you're rating goes from low
attractiveness to high attractiveness,
there on the x-axis.
The amount of romantic attraction you
experienced for the person goes up
sharply.
Now, this is crucial.
If it's the case that people who say, I'm
actually not that interested in romantic
attraction, it doesn't actually matter
I'm sorry, in physical attractiveness,
that is, it doesn't actually matter that
much to me, then you should be, see a
weaker slope, maybe something like this.
And what that slope would suggest, given
that it's, that it's not parallel to the
black slope.
What you see here is, yes, of course,
it's nice to be with somebody better
looking than somebody worse looking, but
the level of attraction is less strong of
a predictor among people who say I don't
care about physical attractiveness.
But that's not what the data show.
This is what the data show, an exactly
parallel line.
What that means is regardless of what you
told us a week ago of the extent to which
physical attractiveness is important to
you in a mate.
The degree to which you like the
attractive people more than, more than
the unattractive was the same.
Everybody was about equally inspired by
the, by the degree to which the person
was attractive and their previous reports
of how much they thought physical
attractiveness would matter to them was
irrelevant.
How about earning prospects?
Over here on the upper right, you can see
that graph, and what do you see?
Two parallel lines.
People who say they care a lot about
earning prospects, people who say they
don't care much about earning prospects
end up being equally inspired by the
people with high relative to low earning
prospects.
Over here on the lower left, now we have
personable, how warm and kind and
friendly is the person?
Once again, two parallel lines regardless
of how personable you said you wanted
your, how, how important it was for you
that romantic partners are high in
personability, was irrelevant to how much
high versus low personable people matter
to you.
Now, is this a statistical artifact, or a
statistical confound in our design?
Is it the case maybe that people don't
actually have any preferences for
anything?
Well, we want to suggest that the story
is very complicated for mating, for a
variety of reasons, one of which is,
mates vary on a lot of dimensions.
People are very complicated, much more
complicated than say, a sofa.
But also, the mate has to like you back
and these things all factor into the
evaluation.
So we did a final little quirky study
where, where what we wanted to do was see
whether we could find evidence for this
predictive validity hypothesis, for this
hypothesis that, when you say you care
about something, you actually are
inspired by that thing and we looked at
cereals.
Specifically, we looked at the sugar
content of cereals.
People vary in the degree to which they
say they're looking for sugar, they like
sugary versus non-sugary cereals.
And then what we did is we had them
sample a range of different cereals and
their report of those, of how much they
like those cereals was quite different as
a function of whether they really value
sugary cereals or not.
And specifically, the story is this, when
people say they strongly value sugary
cereals, the more sugar content in the
cereal, the more they like it.
If they say that they don't care that
much about how much sugar is in cereal,
then sugar content is irrelevant to how
much they like the cereal.
That is a totally self-evident silly
point, but contrast the slide on the
lower right to the other three slides,
and you can see that there's something
about the mating domain.
We seem not to have insight into what it
is that we like in the mating domain.
What will inspire our attraction?
Even though we a good sense of that in a
simpler domain like cereal.
These are college students at
Northwestern, maybe upper social economic
status on average.
What about middle-aged people?
And what about people who aren't
reporting on initial attraction, but
people who are actually involved in an
established romantic relationship, right?
Would you see the same sorts of patterns?
Maybe, maybe our ideal preferences start,
for a certain trait, start to be much
more important once we're making marriage
decisions for example.
So here, we're looking at the distinction
between, at the correspondence between
what you say is important to you and
what's actually important in a much older
sample.
Specifically, 500 participants and the
average age of these participants was 41
years old.
The procedure was simple, people
completed an online questionnaire, they
were all romantically unattached.
they were single at the time they
reported on that they first started the
study, and they reported their mate
preferences.
So, on a scale from 1 to 9, how much do
you value earning prospects, how much do
you value good looks, etcetera.
And then, we let 2 and a half years pass
and we followed up with the same 500
people again.
And they reported on either a current
partner, if they were involved in a
relationship at this point, which many of
them were or they reported on a desired
partner, the person that they were most
interested in, if they weren't currently
involved with somebody.
And then we accessed romantic interest.
So how romantically attracted are you?
How satisfied are you with this person,
etcetera?
Marriage intentions, to what degree would
you like to marry this person?
And marital status, because some of our
people who were single when the study
started were now engaged or married.
And it turns out as you can see in this
graph, which I won't, I won't present all
the graphs, but this is illustrative,
illustrative.
So on the dimension of warmth, how much
do you care about warmth?
Turns out that people who say they care a
great deal about warmth are equally
inspired by how warm their current
partner is than people who say they don't
care that much about warmth.
And here again, you have two exactly
parallel lines just like I kept showing
you repeatedly.
Now, I won't show you all 21 of the, of
the graphs, but they all basically look
like this and not one of them showed
different lines as a function of whether
you strongly cared about the trade in
question versus said you didn't care that
much about the, the trade in question.
So, let's revisit the two questions, are
there in fact these sex differences that
we all believe to be true?
Is it true that men prefer physical
attractiveness in a partner more then
women do, that women prefer earning
prospects in man more then men do?
No, that is, yes, we have these theories
that we care about those things.
Those theories that we care about those
things influence how we behave when it
comes to online dating or personal ads.
But once we have met somebody in the
flesh and blood, there is no longer any
sex difference in the degree to which and
women care about earning prospects and
physical attractiveness.
Now, the second question is, do we really
know what our romantic preferences are?
That is, can we introspect, do we have
self-insight and know what it is that
really makes us attracted to people?
And here, again, there appears to be no
evidence that we do.
across study after study after study and
analysis after analysis after analysis,
when we look at people who said, I care a
great deal about this characteristic, and
compared them to people who said, I don't
really care that much about that
characteristic.
They were in fact equally inspired,
equally attracted to people as a function
of how much they had the characteristic
in question, like physical attractiveness
or warmth for example.
And finally, I want to call, I want to
come back to the way dating works in the
modern era and ask, is it really sensible
for us to decide or learn who is
compatible with us on the basis of
browsing people's profiles?
And I want to suggest to you that the
answer is, no, that browsing profiles or
20 seconds versus 20 minutes versus 20
hours is not going to give you different
insight into who's compatible with you
and online dating is a very useful tool
as a way to broaden the amount of people
in your dating pool.
But before you start ruling people out on
the basis of their profile, remember, you
might not know your preferences as much
as you thought you did and you might be
spending a whole lot of time browsing
profiles that actually won't be
informative to your mating life.
What I encourage you to do is, sure, use
online dating, use speed dating, and so
forth, but get offline quickly for a
quick chemistry check.
That's the way you're going to learn
whether there's romantic chemistry here.